Is AI making programmers faster? Most
people think so. However, this study
says otherwise. So, I read the entire 50
pages to figure out why are some
developers slower when using AI and what
can we do to not make those mistakes.
This is the main study by company called
Meter. And these guys have worked both
with OpenAI and Anthropic. So, they're
pretty legit. Now, before the study, the
researchers predicted that AI will speed
up the developers by 24%. Surprisingly,
the AI tools actually slowed them down
by 19%. So, I'm not going to waste your
time. I'm just going to show you the
results. This is the impact that using
AI had. There are actually some
additional costs when using AI, such as
reviewing the AI output, prompting, or
waiting on AI that slow the developers
down even further. This is why I'm
making this video. If you don't know
what you're doing, AI will actually slow
you down. However, if you watch until
the end, you'll know how to avoid all of
these mistakes and how to actually boost
your developer productivity. Now, to
start with, who even were the developers
in the study? Well, it was a group of 16
senior open source maintainers with an
average of 10 years of experience. Also,
these guys were not AI noobs. 93% of
them have used LLMs before and 44% of
them had prior experience with cursor.
Now, the main AI tool used in this study
was cursor pro with cloth 3.7 as the
model. By the way, as I was recording
this video, a new study from GitHub
themselves was released. So, it's going
to be very interesting to see if this
study confirms the finding of the first
study or if the results are different.
But more on that later. So here's how
the experiment worked. It was a
randomized control trial. In total, they
did 246 GitHub issues. And each
developer coin flipped to find out
whether he will be using AI or not. Now,
before they wrote any code, first the
developers guessed how long each task
would take, both with AI and without AI.
And the rules were super simple. With
AI, you were free to use basically
anything. Cursor claw, JGBD, whatever
you want. However, without AI, you
couldn't use any LLMs at all. Now, you
might be thinking, "Okay, David, but
what exactly got measured?" Well, the
clock started when the developer began
working on the issue. And it only
stopped after the pull request was
reviewed, approved, and merged. And
here's actually a very interesting
visual from the study of how it broke
down. So, first, as you can see, there
was a list of different GitHub issues.
Those were split into two categories, AI
disallowed and AI allowed, where the
developers worked on the issue until
completion. Then, the researchers
calculated the change in time from AI.
Now, most shockingly, it was actually
faster when the developers didn't use
any AI tools. This goes completely
contrary to everyone's predictions.
experts, participants, everybody was
predicting that AI would speed up those
developers. However, the findings of the
study were the exact opposite. By the
way, Enthropic just released a brand new
AI model, Claude Opus 4.1, and what did
we do? We instantly added into Vectoral.
So, if you have Vectoral Pro, you can
just go to the model selector and select
from any of the models, enable Opus 4.1,
save it, and you can start using it
inside of Veectal Working on all of your
tasks. So, again, go to Vectorai, try it
yourself, you can get started completely
for free. That's right. The AI made the
developers slower. On average, each task
took 19% longer. And this applied for
short tasks, long tasks, easy tasks,
hard tasks. Everything showed the same
slowdown. Here's another visualization
from this study. On the x-axis, we can
see the implementation time in hours. So
most of the GitHub issues took roughly 2
hours. And on the y-axis, we can see the
percentile of observed implementation
time. So this begs the question, why did
the AI slow the developers down? Well, I
think there are three main reasons.
Number one, lack of server reliance.
These devs relied on AI even for simple
things that would be faster manually,
especially for a senior developer.
Number two, a lot of the devs already
knew the answer. Keep in mind, these
guys had five plus years of experience
on these repositories. So AI didn't
really add any new insights or
knowledge. Plus, a lot of these code
bases were huge. I mean, over a million
lines, which easily overwhelmed the
models, limiting how much help they can
do. So, here is my expert opinion as one
of the world's leading AI developers.
There are multiple problems. First of
all, this study was only done on 16
developers, which is a very small sample
size. It was also tested with senior
devs who already have built-in ways of
working, certain habits, certain code
style. These guys are way more picky
about what they accept and what they
reject. Plus, they only used cursor.
They didn't use any advanced AI agents
such as cloth code, devin, codeex,
nothing like that. Plus, AI actually
helps beginners far more than senior
devs. And by the way, I'm not the only
one who found flaws in the study. This
person figured out that using your own
repo isn't that effective. By far the
biggest unlock this guy had was when
using AI to navigate unfamiliar repos.
Like if you join a company and you have
to navigate a complicated codebase, you
can learn the codebase way faster if you
have access to AI tools. Another great
point is that AI tools don't magically
speed you up. Rather, they give you
leverage only if you know how to use
them, which is what my entire channel is
basically all about. So if you want to
be an effective AI developer, make sure
to subscribe. All right. So even though
the developers in this study were
slower, should devs use AI today? And
the answer is yes. Even though this was
a very interesting and unexpected
outcome, I'm still very bullish on
coding with AI. But if you want to use
AI tools seriously and effectively,
there are a few important things you
must know. So, as I promised, let's take
a look at the GitHub study. So, this is
Thomas Dome, the CEO of GitHub. Either
you embrace AI or get out of this
career. In the latest GitHub study, a
striking trend was revealed. Those who
persist beyond early skepticism emerge
with dramatically higher ambition,
technical fluency, and job satisfaction.
AI is on track to write 90% of code
within the next two to five years. Also,
there are new skills that matter now
such as agent orchestration, iterative
collaboration, critical verification,
chrome engineering, you name it. So,
while this GitHub study found that AI
was time-saving, that wasn't the main
outcome. The main outcome was the shift
in ambition. Basically, AI allowed
developers to dream bigger. And as I
predicted, using AI also had a massive
implications for education. This is what
I like to call vibe learning. So if you
want to be on the cutting edge of AI,
listen to the CEO of GitHub and start
adopting AI tools. The first tool that
all of you should adopt is Vectal. It's
an AI agent for task management that can
help you achieve any goal 10 times
faster. And yes, this is the tool I've
built and it's saving me many hours per
week. So if you want to instantly make
yourself more productive, try it
yourself for free. Just go to vectal.ai
and type in whatever goal you want to
achieve. Now, if you've been watching my
channel, which you should, you will know
that AI is much more efficient for
building MVPs than changing risky
production code. And that's really the
main problem of this study. They only
tested AI on existing repositories. They
didn't build anything from scratch. And
that's a problem because building an MVP
is now 10 times faster thanks to AI,
maybe even more, honestly. However,
writing production ready code that
follows existing standards is only 30 or
40% faster if you apply everything from
this video. If you don't know anything,
you'll actually be slower like the study
suggests. So, here are seven tips you
must know about coding with AI. Number
one, use the right model for the right
task. Not all LLMs are created equal.
You need to check its context size.
Compare the official benchmark scores.
Do a little vibe test yourself. And a
great tip actually is that if you use
something like close for set or close
for opus, just check it with a different
model like 03. Don't use the same model
from the same company to verify the code
that an AI agent wrote. So if you use
OpenAI model like 03 or GBD5 coming
soon, just use Gemini 2.5 Pro from
Google to check the output. Pro tip
number two, use AI to build new
features. When you start a new project
or add a new feature, AI speedups can be
insane. 10x, 20x, maybe even 100x if you
really know what you're doing. AI agents
can help you design an entire codebase
in a matter of minutes. Plus, you can
quickly test all kinds of different
ideas from unique angles. Tip number
three, if you are going to be using AI
on large code bases, you can absolutely
do it, but make sure to follow these
rules. Number one, make small focus
changes only. Number two, avoid huge
refactors in one go. Split it into four,
five, six stages. Number three, work in
a feature branch only. Make sure to
create a new branch and work there. Do
not work on staging on main. None of
that. Also, never push directly to main.
No matter how tempting it might be, it
will bite you in the ass in the long
run. And lastly, commit often. Do a
GitHub commit every 10 to 15 minutes.
With AIS, you can have them write the
GitHub message. Write the commit
message. For example, if you use cloth
code, it knows already what you're
doing. Same with Cursor. Same with
Windsor. All of these AI tools, they pay
attention to what you're doing. So, they
can just write the commitment message in
a matter of half a second instead of you
writing a short one or being lazy or
leaving it empty, code forbid. AI coding
tip number four, how to avoid errors
from the start. This is the best
strategy, right? Start by having the AI
analyze the codebase. Do not rush into
changes. Tell it to find all of the
relevant files. Make a list of them and
read through all of them. Also, actually
put in more effort yourself and provide
the LLM with tons of context. Obviously,
keep it related to what you're actually
doing. Next, and this is uh something
that most people like to skip, but try
to understand the feature or the bug
yourself first. I know this is not sexy,
right? Everybody wants to delegate
everything to AI, but if you actually do
this, if you spend a few minutes trying
to understand what's happening yourself,
you can move way faster and you'll be
able to spot when the AI is going off
track. And then a lot of software
development fundamentals such as running
llinters, type checks, automated tests
to catch as many issues as early as
possible. Tip number five, discipline
equals speed. With the correct
workflows, you can work way faster. Your
main takeaway here should be to spend
more time before you have the AI write
any lines of code. The more time you
spend before, the faster you can build a
feature and the less errors you'll run
into. What I do with every single
feature, I create a markdown file. I
type in my exact vision. I lay out the
steps I necessary. I lay out what I
don't understand. I lay out what I
already know. And only then, only after
like 20 minutes of me writing into
markdown file manually with my fingers.
Only then I let the AI do any code
changes at all. Pro tip number six,
context engineering. Clear prompts equal
clear output. Be specific about the
inputs, outputs, and constraints of
every single feature. And make sure to
actually create a markdown file for
every feature. This is very OP because
it can be like a scratch pad for the AI
agent to write notes and for you to
refine your vision as you work. Really,
this is like non-negotiable for me.
Also, make sure to just tag all of the
relevant files. Don't waste the AI's
time, right? The AI can waste your time,
but you can waste its time. If you
already know where the feature should be
implemented or which files the bug is
in, tag them. It will make your AI
agents much better. Trust me. Also start
building internal documents of all the
features, all the parts of your app, all
the data types, architecture,
everything. So you can easily tag these
dogs and not only speed up your own
learning curve or when you hire a new
developer, you can get them up to speed
faster, but you can tag these dogs for
AI and the AI can easily learn and
quickly learn how your codebase works.
Now, you always have to remind yourself
that you as the human are the decision
maker. Make sure to keep the big picture
in the view. Don't trust the AI blindly.
Use it for what it's good at, but don't
trust it for what it's bad at, such as
creativity, taste, naming, codebased
architecture, the most important things
really. When something inevitably
breaks, the best thing you can do is to
use AI to understand the root issue
yourself. I cannot stress this enough.
Upskilling yourself with AI is the
biggest hack. It's the biggest cheat
code that nobody's talking about.
Everybody's like, "Okay, build this, VIP
code this, VIP code that." Guys, you can
literally upskill yourself three times
faster than you could otherwise. Before
AI models, it would take you multiple
years to become proficient at a
programming language. With AI, you can
ask hundreds questions every single day
and it will teach you. It will
reiterate, will explain it in a
different way. It will browse the web to
get examples. It's insane. Use it for
learning. Use it for upscreen yourself.
And not only will you benefit from the
exponential curve of AI, but you will
add another exponential that's even more
steep of your own AI skill set. Now, no
matter what, do not ever delegate your
thinking to AI. I don't really envy the
new generation because all of these kids
are raised with chbpt. But you need to
make product decisions. You need to stay
in charge. You need to have that taste.
You need to trust your you need to trust
and develop your own judgment. Do not
ask the AI what the next feature should
be. You as the founder should know that.
So instead of listening to AI, listen to
your own intuition plus your own users.
Talk to your users as much as possible.
I know everybody in Silicon Valley in
the startup world says this, but guys,
until you actually run a startup, you
don't realize how important this is. The
only thing that really matters is what
the users want. So, build something that
the users want. Now, since you watched
the entire video, I'm going to give you
a little bonus that I discovered today,
and that is giving Cloud Code custom
hooks. So, what is a hook? If you don't
know, a hook is a script that runs
before or after Clude does something
like editing, running a tool, or
stopping. It lets you auto format code,
block risky commands, run tests, send
alerts, or really do anything you want.
Like some people literally have it play
a sound to notify them, oh, CLC has
finished running. So basically, hooks
are automated control over what cloud
code does, allowing you to customize it
in infinite possible ways. Let me show
you. So here I am inside of cursor. I'm
going to show you three different cloud
code hooks all of you should really set
up. And the beauty of this, it takes
like 2 minutes to set up. So let me show
you. First hook is this one. Append
ultra thing. This one I borrowed from
McKay Riley on Twitter, so shout out to
him. But basically the way this hook
works is that anytime your prompt ends
with dash u, it appends this prompt
right here. Use the maximum amount of
ultra think. Take all the time you need.
It's much better if you do too much
research and thinking than not enough.
You have to realize ultra think this
actually has influence on the reasoning
effort of clo code. Enthropic built this
in into clo code. It can recognize four
different words. Think, think hard,
think harder and ultra think. That is
the most powerful level of reasoning
effort. So this isn't just some weird
prompting technique. This actually
directly impacts how many tokens will go
into the reasoning effort of your next
clo response. Now the next hook I built
myself and this one will be
automatically appended anytime you
finish your prompt with dash e. And
here's what it says. Above are the
relevant logs. Your job is to think
harder about what these logs say. Give
me a simpler and short explanation. Do
not jump to conclusions. Do not make
assumptions. Quiet your ego. Assume you
know nothing. If you've worked with
cloth for models or any clo models, you
know like the you're absolutely right or
oh I see the issue now. This is beyond
frustrating, right? And by adding lines
like this, you greatly eliminate it. So
basically the way I use this cloth code
hook is for understanding logs, right?
Maybe I paste in 500 lines of backend
logs and I do e, which is way faster
than typing these six sentences, right?
and Clo will basically explain the logs
to me, suggest what the next step is and
why that should be the next step and
answer in short. So, I use this multiple
times a day and save so much time. Now,
the last hook is actually my favorite
because this one I use virtually after
every single prompt. I mean, you cannot
go wrong by sending this one. And by the
way, I posted this on Twitter and both
of my tweets got a lot of traction. By
the way, if you don't follow me on
Twitter, you really are missing out. But
anyways, this is my golden prompt. This
is like this is a David Andre prompt. So
anytime my message ends with dash d this
gets appended at the end. Think harder
answer in short. Keep it simple. Really
you cannot go wrong with this. It
improves every single output. No matter
if you're asking question or if you're
fixing a bug or implementing a feature
if you just add this at the end of every
single prompt clo will perform better. I
can guarantee you that. Unfortunately
typing these eight words is way slower
than just typing two characters which is
the power of the hook. Now to make these
hooks work, you have to actually add
them to your settings.json file inside
of the cloth folder. And again, if you
get stuck at any point, just go into
vectal, ask the question, and it will
tell you how to set it up. The reason
for that is vectal uses perplexity pro
in the back end. So if you use vectal,
you literally don't have to pay for
perplexity pro. Anyways, here's how it
should look like inside of the
settings.json. So obviously at the top
you have your permissions, list of
allowed commands, list of denied
commands. All of these are in the new
society. By the way, if you're serious
about AI, make sure to join the new
society. But then at the bottom, you
need to append the hooks to kind of
register to them so that they actually
run automatically. Cloudco doesn't use
them. These get executed by themselves
on different actions, right? So, one of
the possible ones is user prompt submit.
Anytime the user submits a prompt, we
check whether any of these hooks should
be activated. And by the way, I just
asked Veil to browse the web and find
the main hooks in cloud code. Here they
are. So, user prompt submit hook. The
one we're using here, pre-tool use hook.
So before using a tool, you can
customize again endless amounts of
actions or checks or tests that should
run before cloud code uses a tool. Then
after it uses a tool, right? Maybe
there's a quick uh backend test you want
to run after uses tool or some llinter.
You can easily do that or a notification
hook, right? A lot of people have a
sound or like a sentence like a human
voice speaking out when cloud code
finishes because um it can sometimes run
for a long time and maybe you switch to
a different tab and do something else.
So yeah, with hooks you can customize
your cloth code experience to your
liking. And that's why I highly
recommend you take two minutes and add
these hooks into your cloth code setup.
It's going to save you so much time. But
hooks are just one part of cloth code.
There is sub aents. There is commands.
Cloth code is amazing. There's a lot to
learn. In fact, I made an entire
workshop called the cloth code mastery
on how to become a top 1% of user of
cloth code. I've used it for well over
300 hours. basically every single day
since it released for like 4 to 8 hours
a day every day. And in this workshop,
not only do I explain how you can go
from complete beginner to top 1% clo
expert, but also I give you all of my
files, I give you all of my prompts such
as the main cloud. MD I'm using. I also
give you my settings.loc.json,
my protocol.md for all GitHub protocols,
all of my cloud code sub aents commands,
the entire stack, everything you might
need. Plus, we host weekly calls where
you can ask anything if you get stuck.
So, if you're serious about coding with
AI, make sure to join the society. It's
going to be linked below the video. And
if you want to participate in future AI
developer studies, go to this link. This
is from the original study. So, shout
out to them. A lot of this in video
would not be possible without them. With
that being said, thank you guys for
watching and I wish you a wonderful,
productive week. See you.